Mazatl’s house was very simple. It was made of adobe clay bricks. The house was one big room divided into separate areas. Vinnie and Mandy met Mazatl’s mother. She was making flat pancake-like bread.
"These corn tortillas are for your papa," she said to Mazatl. "But please take a bath first."
Mazatl led them to another building. "This is our bath hut," he explained.
Vinnie and Mandy saw a mud hut. It had a chimney on the side with a hot fire.
"The chimney heats the walls inside. We throw water on the walls. And we get lots of steam. We come here to get clean, but also when we are sick," Mazatl explained.
"Does it make you better?" asked Mandy.
"Oh yes!" replied Mazatl. "I once had bad pains in my chest. The steam and heat made me well again. You go first," he said to Mandy.
Mandy had a quick steam bath. So did Vinnie. When they came out, Mazatl had fresh clothes for them. Vinnie got a short skirt and a cloak to wear over one shoulder. Mandy got a colorful sleeveless shirt and a skirt.
"My mother and sister wove these clothes," Mazatl said. "You can return them later."
"Thank you, they’re beautiful," replied Mandy.
Then Mazatl bathed and changed too.
"Mazatl and his family are so nice," Mandy whispered to her brother. "I can’t believe the Aztecs make human sacrifices."
Vinnie didn’t want to think about it.
Taking the tortillas from his mother, Mazatl led Vinnie and Mandy to a canoe.
They got to the crowded market. Vinnie and Mandy were amazed! People arrived in canoes or carried their goods on their backs. They could hear voices arguing loudly.
"I need to find my papa," said Mazatl. They walked past people selling many interesting things.
"Are those bear skins?" Mandy asked, pointing to a stack of fur.
"Bears? Those are puma and jaguar skins. Only the rich can afford them," Mazatl explained.
Vinnie also noticed a man holding a bag of something.
"I will give you three rabbits for those cocoa beans!" a buyer yelled at the man.
"Give me five rabbits and two geese," the seller shouted back.
"Are you mad? I don’t have that many animals!" the buyer screamed.
"I’m offering you a bargain! Take it or leave it!" the seller shouted.
"Oh, no!" Mandy said. "I think those two men are going to fight."
Mazatl laughed and said, "Don’t worry. The judges are watching them."
"Judges?" asked Vinnie.
Just then a tall man walked over. He said a few words to the buyer. The man nodded and walked away.
"Our judges are wise and fair," Mazatl said.
"What exactly do the judges do?" asked Vinnie.
Mazatl looked at his new friends strangely. "Judges make sure people behave fairly. We must obey what they say. Surely you know that."